Guide to the Lavington Papers: Stuart Negotiations
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Lavington papers: Stuart negotiations
1771-1799
OSB MSS 43
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.21
(1 box)
The papers include correspondence and copies of legal documents relating to Lavington's secret commission to negotiate with the daughter of the Young Pretender for the return of the jewel of the Order of the Garter, which Charles I had given to Bishop Juxon and which had descended to the Young Pretender.
Lavington, Ralph Payne, baron, 1738-1807
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased on the James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Fund, 1974.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
RALPH PAYNE, BARON LAVINGTON (1738-1807)
Ralph Payne was born in the West Indies in 1738. The son of a governor of St. Kitts, he was educated in England and in 1767 married Françoise Lambertina Kölbel, daughter of Henry, Baron Kölbel of Saxony. After several years in Parliament, he was made Knight of the Order of the Bath in 1771 and appointed Governor of the Leeward Islands. Payne was recalled in 1775, and spent many years in various elective and appointive offices in England. In 1788 he journeyed widely on the Continent, during which his secret negotiations with Charlotte, Duchess of Albany took place.
Payne was created Baron Lavington of Lavington in the Irish peerage in 1799, and was reappointed to the Governorship of the Leeward Islands in the same year. He died at Government House, Antigua, in August of 1807.
Scope and Contents
The Lavington-Stuart Documents are a small group of letters, legal memoranda, and documents concerning two interrelated negotiations between the Stuart heirs and the British monarchy: the Stuart claims for the arrears of exiled Queen Mary of Modena's dowry, and the Prince of Wales's effort to acquire the "George" jewel. This Order of the Garter jewel had been worn by Charles I to his execution in 1649 and was said to be in Stuart hands. The papers span the dates 1771-1799 and are arranged alphabetically by author.
During the 1780s, the Stuart heirs in exile were pursuing a claim for large sums against the British government, based on English agreements concerning the dowry of Queen Mary of Modena made at the Peace of Ryswick (1697). The death of Prince Charles Edward in January of 1788 resulted in changes to the Stuart strategy. The Stuart claim to the throne of Great Britain was asserted by his younger brother Henry, Cardinal of York, copies of whose protestations are found in folders 3-4. The Prince's personal estate, however, was inherited by his legitimated daughter Charlotte, Duchess of Albany, with whom Lavington (then Sir Ralph Payne) opened negotiations in early 1788 for the repatriation of the "George."
Lavington's extensive report to the Prince of Wales on the progress of these negotiations is located in folder 8. It stresses Charlotte's desire for "extreme secrecy" from her uncle the Cardinal of York, and her request that the Crown support her claims on the dowry. Folder 18 contains her authorization of Lavington as her agent in that matter, dated two days after his report and accompanied by a notarized copy of the Cardinal of York's assignment of his own claims on the dowry to Charlotte.
Folder 2 contains the reply of George, Prince of Wales, dated June 28, in which he offers "my dear Payne" his "sacred word" that he will keep the secret because of Charlotte's "delicate situation," as well as assurances that he will assist her suit "whenever her claims shall be transmitted hither."
The documentation of those transmitted claims fills folders 10-15 and includes memorials and memoranda on the responses by other governments to such claims; extracts from the 1697 stipulations; and drafts and summaries of the case prepared by the Roman Catholic conveyancer Francis Peter Plowden. Folder 15 contains a copy of the Foreign Secretary's official reply, written a few days before the death of Charlotte in Bologna in November 1789. The Marquis of Carmarthen notes that there is "little probability of the business succeeding" and strongly doubts a "successful issue" in Parliament. Folder 16 contains a letter by Andrew Stuart, dated 1799, urging Parliamentary supporters of an annual pension for Henry, Cardinal of York to drop the issue of the Stuart dowry claims
The collection also includes a letter to Lavington's wife, "Ladi Pain"; a Papal Chancery document apparently drafted by Henry, Cardinal of York; a copy of Henry's 1788 epitaph for Prince Charles Edward; and a brief note on the still unlocated "George" jewel of Charles I.
Jacobites; Charles Edward, Prince, grandson of James II, King of England, 1720-1788; George, King of Great Britain, IV, 1762-1830; Mary, of Modena, Queen, consort of James II, King of England, 1658-1718; Lavington, Ralph Payne, baron, 1738-1807; Plowden, Francis, 1749-1829; Stuart, House of; Order of the Garter
- Letters and Documents, Series I
  - "Brulaccio"
    - ALS to Frances Lambertina Kölbel Payne, Lady Lavington; Rothen[berg], 1771 Jun 10 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Congratulating her on her husband's being made a Knight of the Bath. Addressed to "Ladi Pain." In French.
  - George IV, King of Great Britain, 1762-1830
    - LS to Sir Ralph Payne (later Baron Lavington); Carlton House, [1788] Jun 28 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Promising secrecy in the matter of the negotiations between Payne and the Duchess of Albany, daughter of the Young Pretender, for the return to England of the jewel "George" of the Order of the Garter, which had been in Jacobite hands since 1688. Also promising assistance to the Duchess in her claim to the arrears of the dowry settled on Mary of Modena by James II.
  - Henry Benedict Stuart, Cardinal Duke of York, 1725-1807
    - Document, signed (copy); Rome, 1788 Mar 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Copy of his first official protest of his rights of succession, made on 1784 Jan 27. Preceded by a note comparing this first text and his more recent protest (1788 Jan 31) In French.
    - Document, signed (copy); Rome, 1788 Jan 31 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Copy of his second official protest of his rights of succession, made on 1788 Jan 31. In Italian.
    - Document, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      "Venerabiles fratres:" partial text of a Papal Chancery declaration concerning relations between the Papacy and Ferdinand, King of Sicily. In Latin. 2 copies.
    - Epitaph on Prince Charles Edward, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Copy of the Latin inscription written by Henry for his brother's monument at Frascati.
  - Lavington, Ralph Payne, Baron, 1738-1807
    - ALS (copy) and AL (draft) to George IV as Prince of Wales; Rome, 1788 May 28 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Describing negotiations with the Duchess of Albany, daughter of the Young Pretender (Count of Albany), for recovering the "George of the Order of the Garter" jewel. Sets forth the "two conditions" of the Duchess: "the transaction shall remain a profound Secret;" and the Prince of Wales will assist the Duchess in her legal claim to the arrears of the dowry of Mary of Modena.
  - Löwenstein-Wertheim-Rosenberg, Dominik-Constantin, 1762-1814
    - ALS to "Madame;" Vienne, 1785 Aug 24 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Concerning his delivery of her letter to the Emperor. Signed: "Rosenberg." In French.
  - Plowden, Francis, 1749-1829
    - "Case for the information of Mr. Plowden", 1785 Jul (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Document: draft of case statement concerning the claim of the Stuart heirs to the dowry of Mary of Modena.
    - "Copy of Mr. Plowden's Opinion;" London, 1787 Nov 8 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Document (copy): concerning the method of application to be adopted by the Stuart claimants.
    - "Draft of the case of Mr. Plowden for the Ministry", 1787 Oct 11 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Document: draft of case presented to the Marquis of Carmarthen, Foreign Secretary of State.
    - "Extracts from original papers", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Copies, with translations, of agreements on Mary of Modena's dowry reached by negotiators at the Treaty of Ryswick (1697).
    - "Memorial concerning the Claim of the Family of Stuart", [ca. 1787] (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Document. Presenting several arguments in favor of the right of "the grandsons of James II" to the dowry of Mary of Modena. Addressed to the Duke of Dorset, English Ambassador to France.
    - "Memoire", [ca. 1787] (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Documents concerning the inheritance and dowry rights of the Stuarts as inheritors of the claims of Clementina Sobieska, daughter of the duc de Bouillon and wife of James, Prince of Wales. In French.
    - Letter (copy) from Francis Godolphin Osborne, Marquis of Carmarthen (later Duke of Leeds) to Francis Plowden, 1789 Nov 4 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Written as Foreign Secretary of State, as Marquis of Carmarthen. Concerning "the little probability" of the success of the Stuart claims.
  - Stuart, Andrew, d. 1801
    - ALS to Baron Loughborough (later Earl of Rosslyn), 1799 Nov 15 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Agreeing to prevent the question of Mary of Modena's dowry from being considered in the negotiations to provide an annual pension of L4000 to the Cardinal of York.
  - Stuart, Charlotte, Duchess of Albany, 1753-1789
    - Document, signed; Rome, 1788 May 30 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Authorizing Sir Ralph Payne to act as her agent for the recovery of the arrears of Mary of Modena's dowry. Signed by "Charlotte Stuart, duchesse d'Albanie;" signed and sealed by Louis Dominique Digne, French Consular Secretary in Rome. In French.
      With: official copy of Henry, Cardinal of York's assignment of his claims to Charlotte, Duchess of Albany. Signed and sealed by Louis Dominique Digne, French Consular Secretary in Rome. In French.
  - Unidentified
    - Notes on the later history of "The George" jewel, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)